Guide to the Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers [Guía a los materiales de Ramón Gómez de la Serna], 1906-1967 SC.1967.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Writings [Escritos], II.
  - Essays and Articles [Ensayos y artículos], 3.
    - Bio, España, política, archivar, ida y vuelta a España, 1949
      Esta es una recopilación de notas políticas que reflejan los puntos de vista de Ramón sobre la Segunda República, la guerra civil, su visita a España en 1949 y sus ideas políticas en general. Proporcionan más contexto para su declarada lealtad a Franco, un hecho que no discutió en "Automoribundia". Mira hacia atrás con nostalgia a la relativa calma de la monarquía, sin simpatía por la República y sus desórdenes, cuyas causas atribuye principalmente a los movimientos socialistas y comunistas. Además de Franco, los únicos políticos a los que se hace referencia son los republicanos, y todos están sujetos a críticas amargas y mordaces: Álvarez del Vayo, Negrín, Araguistaín, Manuel Azaña e Indalecio Prieto. Ramón favoreció el establecimiento de una dictadura militar católica para evitar una revolución comunista y mantener la estabilidad a toda costa. Su viaje a Madrid en 1949 parece no haber sido el éxito que esperaba porque sus impresiones están lejos de ser entusiastas, y parece haber regresado amargado a Buenos Aires. Notas posteriores que comentan sobre el mundo contemporáneo —se hace referencia al misil Polaris— revelan una sensación de creciente aislamiento y desesperación al mundo.
      - "Banquete a Montero Alonso" (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Various Political Notes (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - "Cuestión Española" (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Various Political Notes (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - "Revolución Española" (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - "Biografía política" (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - Various Political Notes (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - "Estado Madrid", 1949 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - "Ida a España" (Box 24, Folder 9)
      - "Concursos/Premios perdidos" (Box 24, Folder 10)
      - "Zancadilla de Madrid" (Box 24, Folder 11)
      - "Poeta/Biografia" (Box 24, Folder 12)
      - "Comida Aguilar" (Box 24, Folder 13)
      - "Biografía, Vuelta de España" (Box 24, Folder 14)
      - "Visita a España" (Box 24, Folder 15)
      - "La verdad de lo sucedido—Revolución española" (Box 24, Folder 16)
      - "Vuelta de España" (Box 24, Folder 17)
      - "Vuelta a Madrid" (Box 24, Folder 18)
      - Notes on Various Topics (Box 24, Folder 19)
      - "Indalecio Prieto" (Box 24, Folder 20)
      - "Biografía Indalecio Prieto" (Box 24, Folder 21)
      - "Azaña" (Box 24, Folder 22)
      - Transcription of Selected Items from Box 24 (Box 24, Folder 23)
    - Notes on Spain [Notas sobre España]
      This section again reveals Ramón's political views, this time more concerned with general reflections and interpretations about the character of Spain, displaying a tendency to take refuge in an idealized concept of the country separate from its inhabitants. There is more evidence of his worship of Franco, as well brief sections on the Palacio de Cristal in the Retiro and on the Escorial, and a large number of notes on Spain's relationship with Latin America, especially concerning the Conquistadors.
      Esta sección revela nuevamente los puntos de vista políticos de Ramón, ésta vez más preocupados por las reflexiones e interpretaciones generales sobre el carácter de España, mostrando una tendencia a refugiarse en un concepto idealizado del país separado de sus habitantes. Hay más evidencia de su adoración a Franco, así como breves secciones sobre el Palacio de Cristal en el Retiro y sobre el Escorial, y una gran cantidad de notas sobre la relación de España con América Latina, especialmente en relación con los conquistadores.
      - "Política/ cante jondo/España" (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - "La indiferencia altiva de España" (Box 25, Folder 2)
      - "Patriotismo español/Españoles/España" (Box 25, Folder 3)
      - "El Quijote/Gentes de España" (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - "España y América/España y los Españoles" (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - "Conquistadores" (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - "Palacio de Cristal" (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - "Descripción del Escorial" (Box 25, Folder 8)
      - "Avilés y Oviedo" (Box 25, Folder 9)
      - "España y los españoles": Various Topics (Box 25, Folder 10)
      - "Calderón de la Barca" (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - "España": Various Topics (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Transcription of Selected Items from Box 25 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Dios
      This section contains Ramón's extensive notes on God and many related aspects of the Christian belief system such as the Devil, Hell and Heaven, Jesus, and the Bible.
      Esta sección contiene las extensas notas de Ramón sobre Dios y muchos aspectos relacionados con el sistema de creencias cristianas como el diablo, el infierno y el cielo, Jesús y la Biblia.
      - "Dios" (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - "El diábolo" (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - "Astronomías y misterios" (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - "Dios/infierno/cielo" (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - "La creación/velocismo" (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - "Dios/la creación" (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - "Dios": Various Notes (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - "Dios/Jesús/la biblia" (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - "Dios/oraciones" (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - "Sacerdote/iglesia/clericalismo" (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - "El mal y el bien" (Box 26, Folder 11)
      - "Dios y el pecado" (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - "Nuestra religión" (Box 26, Folder 13)
      - "La fe/letra de la religión/las palabras" (Box 26, Folder 14)
      - "La atómica y dios" (Box 26, Folder 15)
      - "Sumisión y resignación" (Box 26, Folder 16)
      - "Amor a dios" (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - "Dios y otras religiones" (Box 26, Folder 18)
      - "La virgen" (Box 26, Folder 19)
      - "Privilegios del hombre" (Box 26, Folder 20)
      - "Los fieles/los fanáticos" (Box 26, Folder 21)
      - "Su perdón y su misericordia" (Box 26, Folder 22)
      - "Querella conmigo" (Box 26, Folder 23)
      - "Dios": Various Notes (Box 26, Folder 24)
      - "Dios": Various Notes (Box 26, Folder 25)
      - "Dios": Various Notes (Box 26, Folder 26)
      - "Lo que es dios/teología" (Box 26, Folder 27)
      - "Dios": Various Notes (Box 26, Folder 28)
      - "Dios y el alma" (Box 26, Folder 29)
      - "Dios": Various Notes (Box 26, Folder 30)
      - "Evidencia del dios/el crimen impune" (Box 26, Folder 31)
      - "Virgen Maria" (Box 26, Folder 32)
      - "Principio del mundo" (Box 26, Folder 33)
      - "Dios": Various Notes (Box 26, Folder 34)
      - "Revelación y la biblia" (Box 26, Folder 35)
      - "El rigor de dios y la guerra" (Box 26, Folder 36)
      - "La moral" (Box 26, Folder 37)
      - "Dios y la realidad, la libertad, la nada, la duda, el arte" (Box 26, Folder 38)
      - "Dios y la sciencia" (Box 26, Folder 39)
      - "Ateos" (Box 26, Folder 40)
      - "Ateísmo" (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - "Ateísmo América" (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - "Ateísmo Amércia" (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - "Dios y América" (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - "Filósofos y dios," Manuscript Fragment (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Bellón Wiesner, Waldemar: Untitled Clipping (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Rivet, Paul: "El origen del hombre," Clipping (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - Gómez de la Serna, Ramón: "Dios," Clipping (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - "Artículos psiquiatría y psicoanálisis"
      This folder contains Ramón's notes of a polemical nature criticizing various psychological ideas, perhaps with an implicit tone of self-defense. The increasingly Catholic writer that Ramón has become embraces a Jungian kind of reaction to Freudian psychology. There are two article clippings on Jung's affirmation of the reality of the soul, and several manuscript articles by Ramón in which he laments the absence of the mysterious, 'lo indecible', the soul and God in most psychologies, justifying artistic manic depression, neuroses, and persecution mania as logical and lucid reactions to the reality of the world. The artist's willful madness is not pathological but a supreme form of protest; the idealist's aspiration towards the supernatural is opposed to the scientific investigation of the sinful subconscious, according to Ramón's argument.
      Esta carpeta contiene las notas de Ramón, de naturaleza polémica, criticando varias ideas psicológicas, tal vez con un tono implícito de defensa propia. Ramón, quien se ha convertido cada vez más católico, abraza un tipo de reacción Junguiana a la psicología Froidiana. Hay dos recortes de artículos sobre la afirmación de Jung de la realidad del alma, y varios artículos manuscritos de Ramón en los que lamenta la ausencia del misterioso "lo indecible", el alma y Dios en la mayoría de las psicologías, justificando la depresión maníaca artística, las neurosis, y la persecución manía como reacciones lógicas y lúcidas a la realidad del mundo. La locura deliberada del artista no es patológica sino una forma suprema de protesta; la aspiración del idealista hacia lo sobrenatural se opone a la investigación científica del subconsciente pecaminoso, según el argumento de Ramón.
      - Loose Notes (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - "Afecciones vaporosas" (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - "Maniacos depresivos" (Fragment) (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - "Neurastenias nuevas" (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - "Psiquiatras y depresivos" (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - "El Ru-Ko" (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - "Trepanación" (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - Unidentified Title (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - Unidentified Title ("Cuento psiquiátrico") (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - Published Clippings (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Biographies [Biografías], 4.
    Ramón authored or planned biographies about several individuals, including Ortega y Gasset, Pablo Picasso, Unamuno, and Valle-Inclán. This subseries comprises the drafts, notes, manuscripts, and clippings that were produced during the writing and research on these projects. Each section in this subseries deals with a specific individual.
    Ramón escribió o planeó biografías sobre varios individuos, incluidos Ortega y Gasset, Pablo Picasso, Unamuno y Valle-Inclán. Esta subserie comprende los borradores, notas, manuscritos y recortes que se produjeron durante la redacción e investigación de estos proyectos. Cada sección de esta subserie trata con un individuo específico.
    - José Ortega y Gasset
      Ramón's writings compiled here mainly concern Ortega's arrival in Argentina at the outbreak of World War II. They present Ramón's fragmented perceptions of Ortega: admiration for his independence and stimulating thought and at the same time a critical view of his philosophy, in which Ramón laments a lack of importance given to death and the spiritual, religious dimension, stressing its ironic "chulo" aspect. He was also troubled by Ortega's long silence concerning the civil war. Also featured is a large collection of newspaper clippings, academic articles, and graphic material about and by Ortega y Gasset, with some autograph annotations, handwritten notes, and a drawing by Ramón.
      Los escritos de Ramón compilados aquí se refieren principalmente a la llegada de Ortega y Gasset a la Argentina en el estallido de la Segunda Guerra Mundial. Presentan las percepciones fragmentadas de Ramón sobre Ortega y Gasset: admiración por su independencia y pensamiento estimulante y, al mismo tiempo, una visión crítica de su filosofía en la que Ramón lamenta la falta de importancia dada a la muerte y la dimensión espiritual y religiosa, destacando su irónico aspecto "chulo." También estaba preocupado por el largo silencio de Ortega y Gasset sobre la guerra civil. También se presenta una gran colección de recortes de periódicos, artículos académicos y material gráfico sobre y por Ortega y Gasset, con algunas anotaciones, notas escritas a mano y un dibujo hecho por Ramón.
      - "Ortega biografia" (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Loose Notes by Ramón (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - Loose Notes by Ramón (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - "Con Don José" (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - "De butaca a butaca: Con el filósofo de España" (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - "Ortega y Gasset se fue" (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - Clippings by Ortega y Gasset, 1928-1955 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Clippings about Ortega y Gasset (Authors A-E), 1940-1955 (Box 29, Folder 8)
      - Clippings about Ortega y Gasset (Authors F-I), 1955 and undated (Box 29, Folder 9)
      - Clippings about Ortega y Gasset (Authors L-O), 1929-1956 (Box 29, Folder 10)
      - Clippings about Ortega y Gasset (Authors R-Z), 1955-1956 (Box 29, Folder 11)
      - Clippings about Ortega y Gasset, (Unidentified Author), 1931, 1955, and undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
      - Clippings about Ortega y Gasset, (Unidentified Author), 1955 and undated (Box 29, Folder 13)
      - Clippings about José Ortega Munilla, Ortega y Gasset's Father (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Clippings of Photographs of Ortega y Gasset (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - Clippings of Photographs of Ortega y Gasset with Others (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - Portraits and Caricatures of Ortega y Gasset (Box 30, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous Clippings Relating to Ortega y Gasset (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Goya
      This section comprises material compiled by Ramón for his biography on Goya. Included are many clippings of Goya's art, as well as Ramón's handwritten notes and manuscript pages for the biography.
      Esta sección comprende material compilado por Ramón para su biografía sobre Goya. Se incluyen muchos recortes del arte de Goya, así como las notas manuscritas de Ramón y las páginas de manuscritos para la biografía.
      - Clippings of Goya's Art (Box 31, Folder 1-7)
      - "Una colección particular. Goya, Los López, Sorolla." Article Clipping from ABC, undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - "Desnudo de la duquesa," Loose Notes (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - "Desnudo de la duquesa," Loose Notes and Clippings (Box 31, Folder 10)
      - "Desnudo de la duquesa," Manuscripts (Box 31, Folder 11)
      - Article Clippings by Others about Goya's Works (Box 31, Folder 12)
      - "Elementos gráficos para 'Goya total': La Duquesa de Alba, La Maja vestida, La Maja desnuda," Clippings (Box 31, Folder 13)
      - Clippings of Goya's Portraits, Birthplace, and Copy of One of His Handwritten Letters (Box 31, Folder 14)
      - Clippings of Goya's Paintings (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - Clippings of Goya's Portrait Paintings: Men (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - Clippings of Goya's Portrait Paintings: Women (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - Clippings of Goya's Religious Paintings and Sculptures (Box 32, Folder 4)
      - Photos and a Postcard of Goya's Works (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Carolina Coronado
      Carolina Coronado Romero de Tejada was a Spanish author and Ramón's aunt. He published a book about her in 1942 entitled Mi tía Carolina Coronado (Editorial EMECE, Buenos Aires). Documents in this section include a radio script in dialogue form between Ramón and his aunt (in L. Sofovich's hand), lecture sheets, and two autograph letters; one from Ramón's cousin Rubén, dated December 4, 1929, in Segovia, in which he supplies information for the biography; and the second from Carolina to Rubén, dated May 1909. In addition, there are article clippings reviewing the book, including one by Julio Gómez de la Serna, his brother.
      Carolina Coronado Romero de Tejada era una escritora española y tía de Ramón. Publicó un libro sobre ella en 1942 titulado "Mi tía Carolina Coronado" (Editorial EMECE, Buenos Aires). Los documentos en esta sección incluyen un guión de radio en forma de diálogo entre Ramón y su tía (en puño y letra de L. Sofovich), hojas de conferencias y dos cartas firmadas: una del primo de Ramón, Rubén, con fecha del 4 de diciembre de 1929, en Segovia, en el que proporciona información para la biografía; y la segunda de Carolina a Rubén, con fecha de mayo de 1909. Además, hay recortes de artículos que revisan el libro, incluido uno de Julio Gómez de la Serna, su hermano.
      - Correspondence Carolina Coronado – Rubén – Ramón - Horacio Perry, 1909, 1929, and undated (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Clippings of Pictures Related to Carolina Coronado (Box 33, Folder 2)
      - Clippings of Articles About Carolina Coronado (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - Clippings of Articles by Unidentified Authors Related to Carolina Coronado (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - Clippings of Poetry by Carolina Coronado (Box 33, Folder 5)
      - Notes by Ramón (Box 33, Folder 6)
      - Manuscript Fragments by Ramón (Box 33, Folder 7)
      - "Archivar: Emisión Carolina Coronado," Radio Script (Box 33, Folder 8)
      - "Carolina Coronado: La gran poetisa del romanticismo," Manuscripts (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Picasso
      This section comprises mainly newspaper clippings on Picasso, plus two articles and one manuscript on the artist and his work by Ramón.
      Esta sección comprende principalmente recortes de periódicos sobre Picasso, más dos artículos y un manuscrito de Ramón sobre el artista y su obra.
      - Clippings of Picasso's Art (Box 33, Folder 10-11)
      - Clippings of Picasso and Family (Box 33, Folder 12)
      - Clippings by and on Picasso (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Clippings on Picasso by Unidentified Authors (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Clippings on Other Painters (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Clippings about Picasso's Women and Muses (Box 34, Folder 4)
      - Notes and Manuscript on Picasso by Ramón and Some Clippings (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Macedonio Fernández
      Featured here are a collection of letters and dedications from the Argentinian writer to Ramón from 1928 to 1949, plus many of Ramón's handwritten notes and published clippings. The letters convey Macedonio Fernández ideas on literature and comment on Ramón's work. The notes contain Ramón's reflections on Fernández and were not included in the portrait published in Retratos Contemporáneos in 1941.
      Aquí se presenta una colección de cartas y dedicatorias del escritor argentino a Ramón de 1928 a 1949, además de muchas de las notas escritas a mano por Ramón y recortes publicados. Las cartas transmiten ideas de Macedonio Fernández sobre literatura y comentarios sobre el trabajo de Ramón. Las notas contienen las reflexiones de Ramón sobre Fernández y no se incluyeron en el retrato publicado en "Retratos Contemporáneos" en 1941.
      - Loose Notes by Ramón (Box 34, Folder 6)
      - Clippings of Writings by Macedonio Fernández (Box 34, Folder 7)
      - Clippings about Macedonio Fernández (Box 34, Folder 8)
      - Clippings of Writings by Adolfo Fernández de Obieta, 1940-1941 (Box 34, Folder 9)
      - Clippings of Portraits of Macedonio Fernández (Box 34, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence from Macedonio Fernández to Ramón, 1928-1949 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Ramón María del Valle-Inclán ("Valle")
      This section contains Ramón's notes and a revised manuscript fragment, plus article and image clippings on the Spanish playwright and author. In respect to content, it appears that there is not much additional material compared to Ramón's published biography of Valle-Inclán beyond a few phrases of admiration and a new comparison with a marabou illustrated by the author's drawings.
      Esta sección contiene las notas de Ramón y un fragmento revisado del manuscrito, además de recortes de artículos e imágenes sobre el autor y dramaturgo español. Con respecto al contenido, parece que no hay mucho material adicional en comparación con la biografía publicada por Ramón de Valle-Inclán más allá de unas pocas frases de admiración y una nueva comparación con un marabú ilustrado por los dibujos del autor.
      - Loose Notes (Box 34, Folder 12)
      - Clippings of Images of Valle-Inclán (Box 34, Folder 13)
      - Typed Manuscript Fragments (Box 34, Folder 14)
      - Article Clippings of Valle-Inclán's Writings (Box 34, Folder 15)
      - Article Clippings about Valle-Inclán (Box 34, Folder 16)
    - Resumen cronológico Van Gogh
      This section contains many notes for an unfinished biography of Van Gogh and an extensive chronological narration of his life in manuscript form, which was probably written between 1945 and 1950.
      Esta sección contiene muchas notas para una biografía inacabada de Van Gogh y una extensa narración cronológica de su vida en forma de manuscrito, que probablemente fue escrita entre 1945 y 1950.
      - Notes on Van Gogh (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - "Ultimo momento de su locura-suicidio" (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - Notes on Van Gogh (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - "Autorretrato" (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - "Mitos-Símbolos" (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Unidentified Manuscript (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - Unidentified Manuscript (Box 35, Folder 7)
      - Unidentified Manuscript (Lecture) (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - Unidentified Manuscript (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - Unidentified Manuscript (Box 35, Folder 10)
      - Article Clipping (Fragment) by Ramón on Van Gogh (Box 35, Folder 11)
      - "Grafica:" Clippings of Van Gogh's Art (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - Unamuno
      In a letter to Luis de Olarra, dated February 6, 1958, Ramón explains that he tore up most of the drafts of his Unamuno biography. This section holds what is left of Unamuno-related materials, such as clippings of Unamuno poetry with Ramón's notes, notes on existentialism, ideas on the role of literature and prose, a typescript article on "Unamuno y el sueño de la vida," sent to Cela, who apparently rejected it for publication; and article clippings by Ramón's and others on Unamuno.
      En una carta a Luis de Olarra, fechada el 6 de febrero de 1958, Ramón explica que rompió la mayoría de los borradores de su biografía de Unamuno. Esta sección contiene lo que queda de materiales relacionados con Unamuno, como recortes de poesía de Unamuno con las notas de Ramón, notas sobre el existencialismo, ideas sobre el papel de la literatura y la prosa, un artículo mecanografiado sobre "Unamuno y el sueño de la vida", enviado a Cela, quien aparentemente lo rechazó para su publicación; y recortes de artículos de Ramón y otros de Unamuno.
      - Loose Notes by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - "Unamuno y el sueño de la vida" (Box 36, Folder 2)
      - Unidentified Manuscript Fragment by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - Clippings of Unamuno's Poetry with Notes by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 4)
      - Article Clippings on Unamuno by Ramón and Others (Box 36, Folder 5)
      - Clippings of Unamuno and His Home (Box 36, Folder 6)
      - Loose Notes by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - José Gutiérrez Solana
      José Gutiérrez Solana was a Spanish painter and writer, who created the well-known painting of Ramón's literary and artistic circle members "La Tertulia del Café Pombo." This section comprises notes and manuscript material by Ramón on Solana, as well as documents authored by Solana himself such as manuscript material with autobiographical information, essays, and letters written to Ramón.
      José Gutiérrez Solana fue un pintor y escritor español, que creó la conocida pintura de los miembros del círculo artístico y literario de Ramón "La Tertulia del Café Pombo". Esta sección comprende notas y material manuscrito de Ramón sobre Solana, así como documentos escritos por el propio Solana, como material manuscrito con información autobiográfica, ensayos y cartas escritas a Ramón.
      - "Aventura amorosa," Manuscript by Solana (Box 36, Folder 8)
      - "El Café Candelas," Manuscript by Solana (Box 36, Folder 9)
      - "Un coleccionista," Manuscript by Solana (Box 36, Folder 10)
      - "Excursión a Sevilla," Manuscript by Solana (Box 36, Folder 11)
      - "Un gastrónomo," Manuscript by Solana (Box 36, Folder 12)
      - "La miniatura," Manuscript by Solana (Box 36, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence and Autobiographical Summary from Solana to Ramón, 1941 and undated (Box 36, Folder 14)
      - "Solana al Rastro," Loose Notes by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 15)